Abraham: Two of the main areas that
can be vulnerable to attack from
cyber criminals are the hardware
and software of a computer system
so let’s have a look at these two
areas and how they can be affected.
Hardware is the physical components
of a computer system and covers
everything a system needs to function
including computer chips, motherboard,
graphics card, CPU [central processing
unit], ventilation fan, RAM,
HDD, webcam and power supply etc.
Larger organisations have computer
systems involving large servers such
as mainframes integrated with storage.
All electronic devices including
smart appliances, computers and mobile
devices, to large computer systems
are run by semiconductor integrated
circuits, also known as computer
chips and these can be at risk
during the design and manufacturing
process, of being altered maliciously.
Malicious hardware in the form of chips
can remain dormant for months or years
before being used to launch an attack.
Often security in 'chip' production
is not always looked upon as an
issue, but this form of hardware
vulnerability can affect devices from
smart phones to major defence systems.
An example of this was the Spectre
and Meltdown vulnerabilities
that were identified in 2018.
These were design flaws in chips that
have been in production since 1995
that meant criminals could bypass
some of the most fundamental low-level
security mechanisms and access things
like passwords and encryption keys.
The Operating system or OS is the
software that enables computer
hardware to communicate and operate
all the other software that is
subsequently loaded onto the computer.
Every computer must have at least one
operating system to run other programs.
It speaks the computers language
and therefore talks to the software.
The operating system has many
functions including managing
memory, files, processes, system
and devices and Security of course.
Operating systems should always be
kept up to date to maintain that
security, so regular updates should
be scheduled to protect from malware
threat and unauthorised access.
As well as keeping the OS updated other
software should be kept up to date so
that any bugs or patches can be added
to keep the software malware free.
There are a range of different operating
systems available, and these will depend
on the type of computer system being used.
All computers should have a security
system in place with antimalware software.
This may be part of an internet supplier
package including firewalls and VPN.
Or it may be a standalone antimalware
software package which should be
regularly updated or run continuously.
This will seek out any threats
that may affect a computer system.
Some users stick to free antimalware
software, but this does not protect a
system as much as paid for programs.
Antimalware packages should protect
systems from the latest virus, malware,
spyware, and ransomware attacks whilst
maintaining a user’s privacy and identity
especially when browsing the web.